Joe 你走到哪兒了?
Joe,what's your 20?
快到頭了 我在檢查旋轉木馬
Almost done with rounds. Just checking the carousel.
需要增援嗎? 我都要睡著了
You need some backup? I'm falling asleep here.
不用 給我留一杯咖啡吧
No. But could you leave a cupful of coffee in the pot?
誰在那兒?
Anyone back here?
這是私有財產
This is private property.
5秒鐘之內出來
I'm gonna give you 5 seconds to come on out.
好玩是吧 Don
Funny,don.
我就是找點樂子 開個小玩笑嘛
I'm a man of simple pleasures, and that was one of them.
你在那兒幹嗎?
What are you doing back here?
調整一下校時齒帶 你在這兒幹什麼?
Switching out a timing belt. What are you doing back here?
我好像看見有人在這兒
Thought I saw someone messing around.
- 沒有 就我一個人 - 不是你
- Nah,it was just me. - It wasn't you.
- 讓它停下 - 什麼?
- Turn it off. - What?
關掉!
Turn it off!
什麼?
What?
- Ed? - 收到
- Ed? - Go ahead.
你得叫人來了
You need to send that backup.
我看5步之內將軍 你說呢?
I see checkmate in 5. What do you see?
我覺得只要3步
I see it in 3.
- 我們都很想你吶 - 謝謝
- We've missed you out here. - Thank you. Thanks.
我 呃 我需要休整一陣子
I,uh,i had to take a little break.
- 為什麼? - 我以前和組堛漱@個朋友下棋
- How come? - I used to play with a co-worker friend of mine.
他可能是我遇到的最強的對手
He's probably the best mind I ever went up against.
有一天 他突然決定收手了
One day,he just decided that he didn't want to play anymore.
- 所以你也放棄了? - 正相反
- So you gave up,too? - Just the opposite.
我試了棋盤上的每一步走法
I attempted to play through every permutation of moves on a chessboard.
那得玩多少盤啊
That's an infinite number of games.
也不是無窮無盡的 只是數量龐大而已
It's not infinite. It's just-- it's exponentially large.
你不可能每一種都玩到過
You couldn't have played through them all.
平均每盤棋要走40步 這麼說吧
There's an average of 40 moves per chess game, and i'll tell you something--
我下得越多 越覺得每一盤棋
The more I played, the more I realized that every single match, every single chess game,
每盤棋都只是同一個套路的不同變化
Is really just a simple variation on the exact same theme. You know?
激進的開局 耐心地過招 最後將軍
It's aggressive opening, patient mid-game, inevitable checkmate,
於是我明白他為什麼不再下棋了
And I realized why my friend quit.
他厭倦了週而復始的方式 想要有不同的結果
He was tired of repeating the exact same patterns and expecting a different outcome.
你是說你有用不完的招數 就放在那兒等著積灰?
So you have a lifetime of chess strategy in your head and you're just sitting on it.
JJ: 有案子
我還是會用到的 只不過
I still use it. I just,uh...
用在別的地方 我得走了
I apply it differently. I have to go.
很高興見到你
It was good seeing you.
Rita Stuart 25歲 大西洋城的第二名受害者
Rita stuart,25, second victim in atlantic city.
棄屍地點很引人注目
Pretty public spot for a dump site.
嚴格地說 我覺得是陳屍地點
You know,technically, I think it would qualify more as a disposal site.
沒人會隨便把屍體扔在旋轉木馬上
You don't leave a body on a merry-go-round out of convenience.
他還下功夫打扮了一番 不是嗎?
He took some time with her appearance,didn't he?
指甲磨過 頭髮剪過 衣服是全新的
Yeah. Her nails were polished, her hair was cut, clothes were brand-new.
希望她被發現的時候好看 這帶有明顯的自責
Wants her to look her best when found. That's a lot of remorse.
- 第一個受害人是誰? - Stacia Jackson 29歲
- Who is victim number one? - Stacia jackson,29.
在當地的一個遊樂場媯o現的
She was found at a local playground.
被害者類型發生變化了
A change in victimology.
這些女性之間有什麼聯繫?
What's the connection between these women?
什麼都沒有 Rita已婚 Stacia還單身
There is none. Rita was married, stacia was single.
Rita在小餐館工作 Stacia是公司法律顧問
Rita worked at a diner, stacia was a corporate lawyer.
根據信用卡記錄 她們的活動範圍相去甚遠
According to their credit cards, they never came within 10 miles of each other.
這兩人都是兩個月前被綁架的?
Both women were taken 2 months ago?
是的 她們過著完全不同的生活
Yeah. They lived such completely different lives,
警方之前並未把兩起綁架聯繫在一起 直到現在
The police didn't tie their abduction together until now.
有過性侵犯嗎?
Was there any evidence of sexual assault?
沒有任何暴力的痕跡
There was no evidence of violence of any kind.
那她們是怎麼死的?
So how did they die?
Rita死於中風 Stacia是腦出血
Rita had a stroke, stacia had a brain hemorrhage.
看這個 不明嫌犯給他們注射藥物 卡肌寧 多沙氯銨
Look at this, the unsub gave them a battery of drugs-- atracurium,doxacurium.
都是神經抑製藥物 阻礙大腦傳向肌肉的信號
These are neural inhibitors. They block signals from the brain to the muscles.
他讓她們藥物昏迷兩個月
He put them in medical comas for 2 months.
實際上 她們沒有昏迷
Actually, they weren't in a coma.
還需要鎮靜安眠劑才能昏迷 她們沒有
You'd need phenobarbital to keep them unconscious, and they didn't have that.
等等 受害者被麻痹了但是還有意識?
So,wait a minute. These victims were paralyzed but they were still conscious?
她們看得見 聽得見 可能還有痛感
They could open their eyes,hear, probably even feel stimulation.
身體靜止但是頭腦清醒
Physical immobility but mental awareness.
不明嫌犯想要完全控制她們
This unsub wants total domination over them.
為此 他把她們完全禁錮起來
And he turns their bodies into prisons to do it.
犯罪心理 第五季 第12集 怪誕山谷
Criminal Minds Season05 Episode12 The Uncanny Valley
Mildred Lisette Norman寫道 (美國和平主義者)
Mildred lisette norman wrote,
"任何你不願放棄的東西 一旦超出它的效用 就會佔有你"
"anything you cannot relinquish "when it has outlived its usefulness, "possesses you,
"而在這個物慾橫流的時代 很多人被他們的財產所掌控"
"and in this materialistic age, a great many of us are possessed by our possessions."
讓女性癱瘓但保有意識 性虐待狂的表現
Keeping women in a conscious paralysis reads as sadism.
滅絕人性 把她們當做物品對待
Definitely dehumanizing, reducing them to objects.
可是只有側寫 沒有其他佐證
But there's nothing else about this profile that takes us down that path.
這些女性死的時候都很健康
These women were found in excellent condition.
沒有褥瘡 通過靜脈注射供給營養
There was no evidence of bed sores, they were well fed through an i.v.
可以接觸到注射用品和藥物
His access to i.v.s and drugs--
他一定有些醫學基礎
He almost certainly has medical training.
嫌犯確定是男性嗎?
Are we sure this is a he?
他對受害人的關照
The care this unsub shows these victims,
雖然慘無人道 但側寫表明是女性所為
although they are dehumanized, the profile says female.
擺放屍體的時候怎麼辦?
What about the postmortem posing?
女性可搬不動那麼重的屍體
That's a lot of dead weight for a woman to carry.
這些女人都很嬌小 還不到90斤重
These women are petite. They're under 100 pounds.
好吧 重新側寫了性別 還有什麼變化?
All right,if we reconsider the gender of the profile, what changes?
一樣的 只會更靠譜
Nothing. If anything, it fits better.
男性為了滿足性衝動殺人 女性不會
Men kill to fulfill a sexual compulsion. Women don't.
這在妥善處理屍體的女性殺手中很常見 比如Genene Jones和Amy Archer
You see this in angel of mercy killers, like genene jones and amy archer.
她們無所謂人種或者頭髮顏色 男人才會在意
They didn't care about race or hair color. It's men that do.
頂起 只有男人才會在意
Damn straight. Men do.
嗨 紅頭髮 你看你 夥計們
Well,hello,red. Look at you. Guys.
Garcia 從不明嫌犯給被害人 穿的衣服上有什麼發現?
Garcia,what did you find out about the clothing the unsub's dressing the victims in?
首先兩件衣服都是雪紡綢的
At first only that both garments were made from chiffon,
但是有大西洋城警方的通力合作 和我對時尚的敏銳洞察力
But with the wonder twin powers of the atlantic city police and my impeccable eye for fashion,
我們發現這些衣服都超級合身
We have also determined that these garments fit ridiculously well.
很貼合受害人的身材
They're super flattering to each victim's exact measurements,
像是不明嫌犯親手做的
Kind of exactly like the unsub whipped them up herself.
- 這就是受害者之間的聯繫吧 - 怎麼說?
- Maybe that's what connects the victims. - How so?
也許她殺害較小的女性
Maybe she isn't just killing petite women
不只是因為她們容易被誘拐 而是因為特定的體形
Because they're easier to abduct and pose but because of a physical type.
她需要某種身材
She wants a body type.
為她們製作特別尺寸的衣服
Sewing clothes for a specific size of woman.
別告訴我她殺了這些人 只是想要人體模特
Please tell me she is not killing these women because she needs human models.
肯定還得有別的理由吧
I mean,there's gotta be more to it than that.
說不定是有
There probably is.
起碼在受害人研究上有進展了
But at least we have a start on the victimology.
Prentiss和Morgan去找受害人家屬
Prentiss and morgan, I want you to interview the victims' families.
瞭解她們的生活方式
Talk to them about lifestyle choices.
對於身材形象有沒有什麼顧慮
Any body image issues these women may have had.
Reid 去Rita Stuart的驗屍官那
Reid,go to rita stuart's autopsy,
看看不明嫌犯用的藥物 有什麼特殊的地方
See if the drugs point to any specific medical training the unsub might have had.
Dave和我去陳屍地點
Dave and I will go to the disposal site.
- 還有 Garcia - 在
- And,garcia. - Sir.
你去查一下過去兩個月的失蹤人口記錄
I want you to check missing persons reports for the last 2 months.
看看有沒有類似的綁架案件
See if any abductions match what we know.
我們得確定不明嫌犯有沒有拐走其他人
We need to find out if the unsub's already taken another victim.
亞特蘭大城警局
******
Jareau探員? 我是Marty Cotrone警探
Agent jareau? Detective marty cotrone.
這兩位是特別督察探員 Morgan和Prentiss
These are ssas morgan and prentiss.
- 你聯繫到家屬了嗎? - 他們已經到了
- Were you able to contact the families? - They're already here.
他們帶了我們要的照片嗎?
Did they bring the pictures we asked for?
是的 這讓他們很困惑
Yeah. They were pretty confused by that.
坦白說 我也不是很懂
And to be honest, so am i.
Morgan探員 我不明白
Agent morgan, I don't understand.
我女兒長什麼樣子和 殺了她的兇手有什麼關係?
How does what my daughter looked like have to do with the monster who killed her?
我們認為 不明嫌犯尋找的是某種身材
We think the unsub is looking for a physical type.
健美 但是小巧
Fit but petite.
就是她 這是我老婆
This is her. This is my wife.
她經常去塑身嗎?
********
是的 我猜是的
Sure. I guess.
她一周至少去3次健身房
She went to the gym at least 3 times a week.
Stacia對她的外表引以為傲
Stacia took pride in every aspect of her appearance.
哪方面?
In what way?
她的衣服什麼的 她很喜歡逛街
You know,her clothes. It was her clothes. She loved to shop.
看起來她走的是波西米亞路線
It looks like she has kind of a bohemian streak going on.
是啊
Yeah.
她一般都去哪兒逛街?
What were her favorite places to shop?
高檔商店
High-end boutiques.
- 很貴的那種? - 是的
- Expensive ones? - Certainly.
- 穿著很得體 - 她很細緻
- And dressed to fit. - She was tiny.
每件事都要考慮到 所以她很在意外表
Everything had to be taken in so she'd look... Her best.
你可以把她常去的地方寫下來嗎?
Would you mind writing down some of her favorite places to go?
這些基本都是二手商店?
So these are mostly consignment and thrift shops?
我們只買得起這樣的
That's really all we could afford.
她有去修改過這些衣服嗎?
Did she ever have these clothes altered?
讓裁縫改一下好更合身?
Uh,tailored to fit her better?
我沒有注意過
I never really paid attention.
她穿過像這樣的衣服嗎?
Would she ever have worn something like that?
她穿過這樣的衣服嗎?
Would she ever wear anything like that?
沒有
No.
Dave!
- 你能聽見音樂嗎? - 能
- Can you hear that? - Yeah.
她把受害者放在一個象徵天真無邪 和童年的地方
She's posing her victims in a place that represents innocence and childhood.
大部分連環殺手都沒有特別幸福的童年
Most serial killers don't have a particularly happy childhood.
我猜她是想讓他們擁有 她從未獲得過的歡樂
My guess is she wants them to have the fun she never got to have.
讓我們設想下她是如何行動的
Let's think about how she's doing this practically.
她怎麼才能把屍體 從車上放到旋轉木馬上?
How's she getting them from her car to the carousel?
她在深夜運屍
She's moving a body in the middle of the night.
必須創造便利可行的條件
She needs to make conditions as favorable as possible.
那她需要一輛可以保護隱私的車子 一輛貨車或箱式車
So she'd need a vehicle that afforded her privacy-- A van or an suv.
可一旦停了車 還是有許多地方要掩蓋
That's still a lot of ground to cover once she parks.
就算這些女性很輕  她也冒著被發現運屍的危險
Even if these women are light, she risks getting caught carrying a corpse.
如果她有醫學背景 或者她使用了輪椅
If she has a medical background,what if she used a wheelchair,
一些可能幫她快速搬運的東西
Something that would help her move them quickly?
如果用輪椅 那意味著她的車有斜坡道
And if she has a wheelchair, that means her van has a lift,
可以幫助她卸載屍體
Which would be helpful to unload a body.
這也說明她有一個殘疾人停車牌
Which also means she has a handicap placard.
可以讓她就近停車
Which would give her the closest place to park.
我叫Garcia把有殘疾人停車牌的車 調出來 謝謝
I'll have garcia pull all vehicles with handicap registrations. Thanks,dave.
把膝蓋彎起來 就可以用杠桿原理把她抬起來
Once I have the knees bent, I can get leverage under her.
通常會有個助手幫我
Normally, an assistant helps me.
不過我也可以自己做 如果必須的話
But I can do it by myself if I need to.
假設不明嫌犯也有過這樣的訓練
I'm assuming the unsub would have this training,too.
我問下 這一訓練有沒有什麼特殊要求
Let me ask you this-- is there anything specific about it?
沒有 任何醫護人員都可以做到 醫生 護士 或護理員
No,any caregiver out there can do this-- docs,nurses,orderlies.
你覺得她用的那些藥是從哪兒弄來的?
Where do you think she's getting the drugs that she's using?
她需要操縱醫生或藥劑師嗎?
Do you think she could be manipulating a doctor or a pharmacist,maybe?
如果她操縱了的話 醫生就算是故意失職
He'd be criminally negligent if she was.
有沒有可能 醫生通過住院醫師開方 護士偽造了簽名
But it is possible. I mean,doctors order things through residents, nurses forge signatures,
處方流失了
Prescriptions fall through cracks.
那得流失大量的藥品 得是巨大的疏忽了
That's a lot of drugs and a lot of cracks.
她讓這些女性麻痹了兩個月
She keeps these women paralyzed for 2 months.
你的報告說 她們兩人都被接上了頭髮
Your report said both of them had hair extensions clipped in.
是的 為了掩蓋那些脫落的真發
Yes,to hide the fact that clumps of their real hair had fallen out.
她們被通過靜脈注射 並不是因為她們營養不良 對吧?
But if they were fed through i.v.s, that wasn't from malnutrition,right?
這在臥床不起的病人中很常見
You see this a lot in bedridden patients.
失去了運動機能
Loss of motor function.
特別是像這樣的年輕女性
Especially in a young woman like this.
當然 心理震驚 心理影響付出了生理代價
Of course. Psychic shock. Yeah,the mental effects take a physical toll.
最後一個問題 以你的專業意見
One last question-- in your professional opinion,
你覺得頭髮是在她們生前 還是死後接上的?
Do you think the hair extensions were clipped on before or after death?
- 生前 - 你看起來很肯定
- Before. - And you seem pretty certain of that?
你知道 老太太總說  頭髮和指甲死後還會生長
You know the old wives' tale about your hair and nails growing after death.
不過事實是 由於脫水作用會讓皮膚 產生皺縮 反而使它們變短
What's really happening is that dehydration is shrinking your skin, pulling it back.
根據這些接發的部位 它們肯定是在生前被加上的
Based on where she put these extensions, they were definitely still alive.
我們知道 不明嫌犯沉浸在豐富的幻想
Now,we know this unsub is stuck in a rich fantasy,right?
一個難以置信的詳盡的幻想
An incredibly detailed delusion.
我們不知道她的幻想是什麼 不過肯定涉及到重新塑造這些女性
We don't know what the delusion is, but we know that it involves remaking these women,
從給她們下藥時開始 塑造就開始了
And it begins the moment she has them drugged.
她把她們麻痹了 就可以為所欲為 為什麼還要殺死她們?
So she has them paralyzed and she can do whatever she wants, why is she killing them?
我覺得她不是故意的
Well,i don't think she means to.
大腦就像是一部機器 對刺激產生反應
The brain is a machine designed to respond to stimuli.
如果你讓大腦保持清醒 而限制身體活動 機器慢慢壞了 開始掉發
If you keep the brain awake but the body immobile, it breaks down, loses its hair.
兩個月後 機器終於崩潰
After 2 months, it eventually strokes out.
所以殺人並非不明嫌犯的目的 只是不幸的副作用
So death isn't this unsub's goal, it's an unfortunate side effect.
- 完全正確 - 你們有什麼發現?
- Exactly. - What'd you find out?
Rita Stuart和Stacia Jackson 都是購衣狂
Both rita stuart and stacia jackson were clothes hounds,
不過因為她們都身材嬌小 衣服都要做不小的修改
But because they were petite women,they had a lot of their stuff altered.
這可能是不明嫌疑犯發現受害人的途徑
Could be how our unsub is finding her victims.
她可以親手測量她們的尺寸
She gets her hands on their measurements.
可是我們已經排除了裁縫 改衣店 她們沒有交集
But we already exhausted tailors,alteration shops. There's no overlap.
裁縫可能會把一些特殊衣服 交給第三方修改
The tailors might send specialty items out to third parties.
深入調查全面的僱用記錄 看看有誰可能承接了轉包合同
Dig deep into extended employment records and see who they might be subcontracting to.
- Garcia要和我們說話 - 說吧 Garcia
- Garcia needs to talk to us. - Go ahead,garcia.
好啊 親愛的們 我已經掃瞄了失蹤人口報告
Hello,my pretties. I have finished my missing persons sweep.
沒有發現和醫學有關的車輛 不過有兩個符合這樣穿著的新失蹤女性
I've got nothing on the medical vehicle, but 2 new matches on the clothes make the woman front.
Cindy Admundson  她在一家廉價商店前被誘拐了
Cindy admundson.She was abducted outside a thrift store,
Maxine Wynan最後被看見 是在Hillridge購物中心
and maxine wynan was last seen at the hillridge mall.
這聽起來像我們的受害人
That sounds like our girl.
中心埵竟妗蠵像嗎?
Any surveillance footage at the mall?
沒有 那是外面的停車位 抱歉
No. It was an outside parking lot. So sorry.
新的被誘拐者 她們的體型如何?
The new abductees-- What's their physical type?
我看起來她們都很嬌小 馬上發送照片過來
They look pretty tiny to me. I'm gonna send you pictures.
如果想取悅法院的話
Also,if it pleases the court,
我想請大家注意A號證據 時間順序
I would like to direct your attention to exhibit "a," the calendar map.
怎麼了?
What about it?
這兩位新受害人都是在一周前被誘拐的
Both of these new victims were abducted one week ago,
時間在Rita Stuart和Stacia Jackson 的屍體分別出現的前一天
Exactly one day before the bodies of rita stuart and stacia jackson, respectively,turned up.
她只有找到了替代者 才會去陳屍
She doesn't let a body go until she has a replacement.
非常感謝
Thank you so much.
打擾下 需要幫忙嗎?
Excuse me. Do you need some help?
噢 這個斜坡壞了
Oh,the ramp's broken.
需要我叫輛拖車嗎?
You want me to call a tow truck?
我只要把輪椅放上車就能回家了
I just need to get the chair in the van, and then I can go home.
- 我們可以把它放上去 - 你覺得行?
- Well,we could load it. - You think?
當然 我們把它放在後面嗎?
Sure. We'll put it in the back?
- 你進去吧 你拖 我抬起來 - 好的
- Go on in. You pull,i'll lift. - Ok.
1 2 3...
1,2...
好了 我們需要鎖上輪子或做什麼嗎?
Here we go. Do we need to lock the wheels or anything like that?
你真美
You're so pretty.
被害人叫Mary Newsome
Victim is mary newsome.
兩個月前被誘拐的
Abducted 2 months ago.
她今天一早在長椅上被發現的
She was found on this bench first thing this morning.
這看起來像她的風格 這是雪紡綢 而且縫得很合身
Ok,well,it looks like her style. It's chiffon, and it's sewn to fit.
如果她處置了這具屍體 就意味著她最近抓了一個新受害者
If she's disposed of this body, it means she's recently taken a new victim.
我們聯繫Hotch  需要梳理最近48小時內的失蹤報告
We'll call hotch, we'll comb through missing persons reports from the last 48 hours.
- 我去調出來 - 謝謝
- I'll pulling them. - Thank you.
什麼?
What?
這些不是接發
These aren't hair extensions.
- 也許她的頭髮太易斷裂了 - 也許吧 我不知道
- Maybe her hair was too brittle. - Maybe. I don't know.
你知道嗎? 這是假髮 我想是卡尼卡龍(一種難燃纖維)
You know what? This is a wig. Kanekalon,i think.
- 那是什麼? - 人造發 沒有什麼特別的
- What's that? - Uh,synthetic hair. There's nothing special about it.
它被廣泛用於全世界假髮的製造 不過看這
It's used in wigs all over the world. But look at this.
是縫上去的?
O are those stitches?
縫在她頭皮上
On her scalp.
她把假髮縫上去的
She sewed this in.
好的 Wallace 我知道了 謝謝
Yeah. Wallace. I got it. Thank you.
嗨 我想我知道誰昨晚被帶走了
Hey,i think we found who was taken last night.
她的名字是Bethany Wallace
Her name is bethany wallace.
她丈夫說她沒有從乾洗店回來
Her husband says she never came home from the dry cleaners
她在那堸惜U取了衣服
where she stopped off to pick up some clothes.
店堛漱H看見什麼了嗎?
Anybody at the cleaners see anything?
店員正忙著關店
The employees were busy locking up.
不過他們提到轉讓了部分工作 給一些在家工作的裁縫
But they did mention that they do farm out work to tailors who work from home.
好的 我們可以查看誰接了Bethany的衣服
Good. We can match records based on who worked on bethany's clothes.
我們剛從Garcia那兒收到 最近兩個被拐者的照片
We just got the pictures of the 2 recent abductions from garcia.
把新受害人的照片放在 被她們替換的屍體旁
Line up the photos of the new victims next to the bodies they replaced.
也許對我們整理時間線有幫助
That might help us with the timeline.
- 你們發現了嗎? - 嗯
- You guys see this? - Yeah.
她讓受害者們在形態上 一個個匹配起來
She's matching up the victims physically one to one.
她是個收藏者
She's a collector.
我們可以給出側寫了
We're ready to give the profile.
我們要找的不明嫌犯是女性
The unsub we're looking for is a woman.
她是個收藏者  在精神病理學上接近於貯藏
She's a collector. It's a psychopathology similar to hoarding.
我們所說的收藏者  不是指收藏郵票或籃球卡
So when we say collector, we're not talking about stamps or baseball cards.
不是你們的孩子 甚至你們 會追求的普通愛好
It's not what your kids, or even you, might pursue as a normal hobby.
這是一種對事物的愛慕 演變成迷戀
This is an attachment to objects that's become obsessive,
出現在一些反社會和極端內向的人身上
By someone who is antisocial and extremely introverted.
這些人把自己的一部分 依附於他們的收藏
These people attach a part of themselves to their collection.
如果你試圖把他們分開 或者拿走他們的收藏
If you try to separate them from it or take it away from them,
他們會強烈反抗 甚至像精神病人一樣
They will react violently, even psychotically.
他們的大腦額葉前部皮層受到了損傷
They've suffered damage to their prefrontal cortex.
這是大腦用來控制弗洛伊德式的 幻想和現實的部分
That's the part of the brain that regulates basic freudian fantasy/reality.
他們仍有行為能力 例如駕駛汽車 工作 甚至納稅
They can still function, like drive a car, go to work, even do their taxes.
事實上 她擅長有明確目標的工作 比如精細的縫紉
In fact,she excels at goal-oriented jobs, like the precision of sewing.
或者安排誘拐的細節
Or the details of abduction.
但他們已經沒有能力辨別生死
But they've lost their ability to categorize the difference between living and dead,
也無法辨別擁有和失去 那種能力已經喪失 無法挽回
uh,belonging and loss. That has been irreparably destroyed.
那她收集什麼呢 女人?
So,what's she collecting,women?
事實上 她以為她在收集娃娃
Actually, we think she's collecting dolls.
嚴格說來 是置換他們
Technically, replacing them.
我們認為她在最近的三個月 失去了最初的娃娃
We believe that she lost the originals sometime within the last 3 months,
這成為了她的應激來源
And this is what served as her stressor.
她開始尋找替代物 但發現找不到
She searched for a replacement, and when she couldn't find them,
就開始誘拐最為接近的替代品
She started abducting the closest possible surrogate.
不同種族 但體態相近的女性
Women of different ethnicities but of similar physicality.
注射藥物致受害人麻痹 也是她幻想的一部分
The drug-induced paralysis is part of the fantasy.
她將受害人置於無法回話的境地
She puts her victims in a position where they can't talk back
便可以像膜拜丟失的物品一樣 去膜拜受害人
So she can fetishize them like the objects she's lost.
這樣
Look.
我尊重你們的分析 但這個女人 綁架了6名女性 殺害了其中3人
I respect your analysis, but this woman kidnapped 6 women and killed 3 of them.
你們卻說 全都是因為娃娃?
And you're telling us this is about dolls?
最近的一名受害者 不明嫌犯在她頭皮上縫了假髮
This unsub stitched a wig onto the scalp of her latest victim.
這是給瓷娃娃添置頭髮的技術
It's a technique used to attach hair to porcelain dolls.
要記住 收藏者和連環殺手 也有共同之處
And keep in mind, collectors and serial killers do share certain traits.
許多連環殺手都會拿走物件 作為戰利品
A lot of serial killers take trophies,
他們對戰利品的強烈認同 與這名收藏者對收藏品的認同是一樣的
Attaching the same significance to them that this collector does to objects.
但這個不明嫌犯 並非出於暴力目的
But this unsub's intent isn't violence.
她希望能完整自己的收藏 使得自己能掌控生活
She needs this collection to be complete so she can feel in control of her life,
也許是經歷了什麼創傷 需要治癒
Probably to overcome some trauma she experienced.
只有當收藏完整時 她才能有掌控的感覺
She really only feels that control when the collection is complete,
所以她在活著的受害者身上 一次一次地重複綁架的手法
Which is why she's repeating an abduction pattern with living victims.
如果失去了一個娃娃 或者在這個案子
If she loses a doll, or in this case,
如果失去了一個象徵著娃娃的女人 她就得再找人填上空缺
If she loses a woman who represents a doll, she has to replace it.
嫌犯單獨行動 有醫療培訓背景
This woman works alone. We know she has medical training.
去查查因為舉止不雅 而遭解雇的助理護士 或者護理員
Look for nurse's aides or orderlies who were fired for a lack of social graces.
她就算在病床邊 也裝不了好人
She can't fake a bedside manner.
我們相信 她目前從事服裝裁製工作
We believe she's currently working as a tailor or a seamstress,
我們正順著查下去
And we're following those leads now.
一旦任何可疑聯繫 請馬上通知我們
But do let us know if you notice any overlap in your suspect pools.
謝謝
Thank you.
我當然記得Jackson夫人
Of course I remember ms. Jackson.
發生這樣的事 我們都很難過
We were all sad to hear what happened.
你們是否外包過裁縫工作? 有別人做過這活兒嗎?
Do you ever farm out tailoring jobs, someone who might have done this?
沒有
No.
實話跟你說 這麼過時的東西 我們都不會賣
To be perfectly honest, we wouldn't even sell something so dated.
讓我看看
Let me take a look.
- 這是哪堥茠? - 怎麼說? 看出什麼了嗎?
- Where did you get this? - Why? Did you see something?
你看這個雙線鎖縫法
Look at this lockstitch.
是方巾的樣式呢
It's a handkerchief pattern.
絲綢方巾採用這樣的縫法
You see this on silk-sewn handkerchiefs.
這全都是手縫的
And it's all done by hand.
這麼說 這算是她的簽名了? 這對她來說很特別
So this is her signature? This is unique to her.
我就縫不出來 用上機器也做不到
I couldn't do it, not even with a machine.
有什麼店家專門從事這樣的手工縫製嗎?
If there someplace that specializes in handcrafted sewing like this?
不過還能告訴你幾句
No. I'll tell you this much, though.
她幹這活兒 可是有年頭了
She's been at it a long time.
這個女人... 稱得上藝術家
This woman... Is an artist.
Hotch 這位是 Bethany Wallace的丈夫Karl
Hotch,this is bethany wallace's husband karl.
我們帶他來問話
We brought him in for questioning.
你們知道我妻子在哪兒嗎?
Do you know where my wife is?
- 先生 我們正在全力搜尋 - 不 你們得在24小時內找到她
- We're searching for her,sir. - No. You have to find her in the next 24 hours.
Bethany有糖尿病
Bethany is a diabetic.
看 Prentiss探員說 綁架她的 女人受過醫療培訓 所以...
Look,agent prentiss said that the woman who took her has medical training. So...
Bethany能有機會嗎?
Bethany could have a chance?
- 怎麼了?  - 她讓受害者保持在藥物控制狀態下
- What? - She keeps her victims in a drug-induced state.
她們不能溝通
They can't communicate.
- 這些...這些藥物會不會... - 我們還不知道
- These...These drugs, will they-- - we don't know.
但我們正在竭盡所能
But we're doing everything we can.
大伙 這是Sally 好好對她
Everyone, this is sally. Be nice to her.
那麼醫生 如果一名糖尿病患者 被用了這些藥物來維持她麻痹
So,doctor, if a diabetic were given this battery of drugs to keep her paralyzed,
會有怎樣的反應?
what would the reaction be?
糖尿病患者以不同的方式代謝攝入的 所有東西 如食物 飲料 藥物
Diabetics metabolize everything they consume differently-- Food,drinks,drugs.
這些都會不同程度地被分解為血糖
It all gets broken down to blood sugar at varying rates.
最有可能的是 這名患者 在被給藥後幾分鐘就僵了
Most likely, this patient seized up minutes after she was medicated.
這麼說她已經死了
So she's already dead.
很可能 但...還有另外一種可能
Probably. Although... There is another possibility.
Bethany的病情 可能會讓她  比其他受害人更快分解掉那些藥物
Bethany's condition could break down the drugs faster than the other victims.
她可能恢復對身體的控制?
She could regain control of her body?
每一個小時 只要她不出現  就表示希望尚存
Every hour that she doesn't turn up is a reason for hope.
我們還是快沒時間了
We're still running out of time.
就算那些藥物沒害死Bethany 沒胰島素 她也支撐不了多久
If the drugs don't kill bethany, she's not gonna last long without insulin.
看 收藏者們都是誠實的好人
Look,collectors are good,honest people.
你喜歡娃娃 是不會把你 當成個怪人或是戀童者的
Just because you enjoy dolls doesn't make you a freak or a pedophile.
這點我們尊重 先生 但我們要找的 女人對自己的強迫癥已失去控制能力
We appreciate that,sir, but the woman that we're looking for has lost her ability to control her obsession.
為了重做她小時候有過的一種娃娃 她已經殺死了三名女性
She's killed 3 women trying to recreate a type of doll she had as a child.
跟我描述一下那個系列
Describe the line to me.
好吧 受害人都符合一個模式 她們都20多歲 並且都很嬌小
Well,there's a pattern to the victims. They're in their 20s, and they're petite.
大多數系列的娃娃 都以嬰幼兒形象為中心
Most doll lines revolve around infants.
她是讓她們穿得像嬰兒一樣嗎?
Is she dressing them like babies?
不 她不是 她們的服裝都是雪紡裙
No,she's not.Their wardrobe consists of chiffon dresses,
穿著女性一名金髮一名紅髮 還有一名是黑人
worn by one blond woman, a redhead,and a black woman.
那些裙子 她是自己縫嗎?
The dresses--is she sewing them herself?
你怎麼知道這一點的?
How did you know that?
那是Valois系列
It's the valois line.
80年代後期的本地公司
Local company, back in the late eighties.
很可能我們的不明嫌犯 那時候正要進入青春期
Probably when our unsub was prepubescent.
是的 他們宣揚女性主義 和多元文化融合
Yeah. They promoted feminism and multiculturalism.
堅強獨立的女孩子們 就算背景不同 也仍然可以成為朋友
Strong,independent girls from different backgrounds who could still be friends.
Reid 待填的出生證明
Reid. Birth certificate to fill out.
一張描述她們生活的表格 和一個自己做衣服的工具包
A form to describe their lives. And a kit to sew your own clothes.
JJ說過 她縫東西有年頭了
Jj said she's been at it for a while.
很可能從孩提時代起 她就開始縫紉了
She's probably been sewing since she was a little kid.
等一下 先生 這舉辦的是個什麼比賽?
Wait a minute. Sir,what's this contest that they held?
看誰能做出最富創意的娃娃
That was to see who could come up with the most imaginative doll.
縫一條裙子 再寫段文字描述她
Sew a dress. Write an essay to describe her.
如果你贏了比賽 你的娃娃就會 出現在下一年的系列中
If you won the contest, you'd have your doll featured in next year's line.
- 比賽最後肯定沒能圓滿落幕是吧? - 是 是沒有
- I assume that didn't end well,did it? - No,it did not.
這是兒童心理學家用的經典方法
It's a classic tool child psychologists use.
跟我講講關於這些娃娃的故事
Tell me a story with these dolls.
當公司收到 帶有幾乎毫不掩飾的 肉體或性虐待意象的短文的時候
When the company got essays with thinly-veiled references to physical or sexual abuse,
他們把那些參賽表格 和娃娃都交給了警方
They turned the entry forms and the dolls over to the police.
一曝光 這個系列就給毀了
The publicity killed the line.
你說過那公司是本地的 對吧?
You said the company was local,right?
他們可能還保留著留作證物的衣服
They might still have the clothes in evidence.
短文看得怎麼樣了?
How are the essays going?
叫人讀起來實在是非常壓抑
Makes for some pretty depressing reading.
Prentiss倒是挺享受的
Prentiss is having a good time.
這些娃娃都像是小小的時間膠囊
These dolls are all like little time capsules,
只是80年代時裝 在她們身上可不那麼美好
only the eighties fashion wasn't so kind to them.
我很驚訝 居然有這麼多 小女孩知道怎麼做墊肩
I'm surprised how many little girls knew how to make shoulder pads.
你那邊查得怎麼樣了?
How's it going on your end?
我拿到了一份受害人去找過的
I got a list of vendors the victims went to--
店舖 裁縫 之類的名單...
Tailors,seamstresses, that sort of thing.
嘿JJ 你說過什麼方巾褶邊 對吧?
Hey,jj,you said something about a handkerchief hem,right?
這跟她給受害人縫的一模一樣
That's exactly like what she sews for her victims.
參賽表上的名字是?
What's the name on the entry?
- Samantha Malcolm - 她在我的名單上
- Samantha malcolm. - She's on my list.
等一下 夥計們 我這邊有她的短文 就在這
Wait a minute,guys. I have her essay around here somewhere. Right here.
"Sally不喜歡有閃電的房間"
"sally doesn't like the room with the lightning."
不妙啊
That can't be good.
好吧 夥計們 我剛拿到 Samantha Malcolm的醫療記錄
Ok,guys,i just got samantha malcolm's medical records,and...
哦 我的上帝 她注定歹命
Oh,my god, she was doomed.
像艾米莉·勃朗特那般"注定" 像莎士比亞那般"注定"
Like emily bronte doomed, like shakespeare doomed,
像星際迷航堛漪鶡蝷眻L一樣"注定" (迅速掛掉的無名大龍套)
Like red-shirted ensign in "star trek" doomed.
Garcia 她身上發生過什麼事情?
Garcia, what happened to her?
哦 抱歉 好吧 最初10年 什麼事情也沒有
Oh,uh,sorry,uh, well,for the first 10 years,nothing,
而後 她開始接受了 一系列的電擊休克治療
And then she started a battery of electroshock treatments.
10歲的時候? 誰會對一個孩子 實施電擊休克治療?
At 10? Who subjects a child to ect?
那就是他父親Arthur Malcolm醫生
That would be her father, dr. Arthur malcolm.
他經營一家叫"新生活"的面向問題 青少年的 住院式精神療養機構
He runs an inpatient mental health facility for troubled young people called new lives.
起初 Samantha寫的那篇短文 顯現出一些端倪
At first,the essay that samantha wrote raised some flags,
但她父親解釋說 治療是為了應對其母親近期的過世
But her father explained that the therapy was to deal with the recent death of her mother.
在那之後 他開始給他服用 一系列強效治療精神病的藥物
After that,he started her on a serious regimen of anti-psychotic drugs,
直到幾年前 才給她斷掉
Which he weaned her off of a few years ago.
這就解釋了她對藥物的熟悉
It explains her familiarity with medication.
她現在在哪?
Where is she now?
呃 她父親宣稱她殘疾(生活無法自理) 所以 他仍然是她的法定監護人
Uh,her father declared her incompetent, so he's still the legal guardian.
所有的一切都在他的名下
Everything is in his name.
而她所有的資料上 都填著她住在"新生活"
And all of her records list new lives as her residence.
她又不能把受害人關在 一家療養院 她需要獨處
She couldn't keep victims in an inpatient facility. She needs privacy.
Garcia 以他父親名義 所持有的房產呢?
Garcia,what about real estate holdings in her father's name?
只有他自己家  但"新生活"有不少 門診處和過渡中心 遍佈鎮上各處
Just his own. But new lives has a bunch of outpatient and halfway houses all over town.
JJ 她在哪堣u作?
Jj,where does she work?
我這埵釵o在鎮上三處 不同店舖的地址
I have her placed at 3 different shops around town.
好吧 我們分頭去店舖跟療養院
All right, let's split up and cover the shops and the facility.
我想去"新生活" 不管她在不在那  我都去 我想和她父親談談
I want to go to new lives. Whether or not she's there, I want to talk to the father.
不誇張地說 有上百種療法 可用來幫助孩子走出迷惘
There are literally hundreds of therapies to help kids through loss.
電擊休克療法絕不在其中
Electroshock is not one of them.
帶上Rossi
Take rossi.
要好好相處喲 晚點再見
Be nice to each other. See you later.
我們走
We're leaving.
不...不
No... No.
我一頭霧水 先生們
I am very confused, gentlemen.
這和Samantha有什麼關係?
What does this have to do with samantha?
我們需要跟她談談 她在這嗎?
We need to talk to her. Is she here?
不 她在上班
No,she's at work.
她住這嗎 還是你把她搬到 你的某個過渡中心去了?
Does she live here, or did you move her into one of your halfway houses?
實際上 她住我的一套房子
As a matter of fact, she is in one of my houses.
好 我們需要地址
Well,we'll need the address.
我得知道這是怎麼了
And i'll need to know what this is about.
她可能和一系列綁架事件有關聯
She might be tied to a series of abductions.
那不可能 那不是我女兒
That's not possible. It's not my daughter.
Samantha是一個人在那棟房子媔?
Is samantha on her own at this house?
那堥S有其他患者 對吧?
There are no other patients,right?
她覺得那樣最好 而我也同意
She thought that was best, and I agreed.
對 但實話說了吧
Yeah, but let's face it--
- 你很高興她不再用你操心了 - 你再說一遍?
- you're happy that she's out of your hair. - I beg your pardon?
因為 如果你最近去看過她 醫生 你會發現她在做什麼的
Because if you had been visiting her recently, doctor, you would know what she's been doing.
Samantha一直都有問題
Samantha has always been troubled.
已經有三名女性因她而死了
3 women are dead because of her.
- 她是做不出那樣的事情的 - 你確定嗎?
- She's not capable of that. - Are you certain?
我是說 電擊休克治療的影響 特別是那個年紀 是永久性的
I mean,the effects of electroshock, especially at that age, are permanent.
但也許這些你都知道
But maybe you knew that.
Samantha10歲的時候我妻子去世了 她再沒能恢復過來
My wife died when samantha was 10, and she never recovered.
任何方法我都試過了兒童精神病療法 寵物療法 沒有一樣對她有幫助
I tried everything. Child psychiatry, pet therapy, nothing helped.
她不停割傷自己 她很痛苦
She was cutting herself. She was in pain.
這次會面結束
That's the end of this meeting.
你女兒在哪 醫生?
Where's your daughter, doctor?
還有 Rossi探員 如果你在她不明白 自己在做什麼的情況下...
And,agent rossi, if you try to talk to her, a mentally ill woman,
試圖跟她 一位患有 精神疾病的女性說話...
Without her knowing what she's doing--
你知道她禁錮女性的事情嗎?
do you know about the women she's keeping?
沒有醫療顧問或律師在場 你是問不出什麼的
And have no medical or legal counsel present, you'll have no case.
你明白我說的話嗎? 什麼也問不出
Do you understand me? None.
我們會把警力留在這 以防萬一Samantha突然到訪
We'll keep the police here in case samantha drops in for a visit.
- 我們走吧Reid - 我簡單問下 為什麼這些玩具會在這?
- Let's go,reid. - Hey,a really fast question. Why are these toys here?
我在我的治療中會用到它們
I use them in my therapy.
這我明白 但為什麼它們 高高地放在這個架子上
No,i understand that, but why are they way up on this shelf,
放那麼高 小孩子根本夠不到
Away from where any kids can actually reach them?
它們能讓我記起曾經治療過的病人
They're reminders of patients that I've helped.
再問一句 你用這個輔助治療的 小女孩 叫什麼名字
Let me ask you something. What was the name of the girl you helped with this one?
Jenny Larson
Jenny larson.
那這個呢? 用這個輔助治療的 小女孩 叫什麼名字
And this one? What was the name of the girl you helped with this one?
Abigail Moore
Abigail moore.
那這一個呢?
How about this one?
Linda Krauss
Linda krauss.
這些小女孩都是... 我猜都是9-12歲?
These girls are what, they're like 9--9 or 12 years old,i'm assuming?
我博士階段主攻的是 創傷對青春期前女孩的影響
My phd. Is on the effect of trauma on prepubescent girls.
你話娷簸w 我可不欣賞
I do not appreciate what you're implying.
我沒有什麼言下之意 只是做個推斷
Oh,i'm not implying anything. I'm making an inference.
推斷是有一定依據的猜測
An inference is an educated guess.
而在此基礎上 我得出了一個假說
And based on that, I form a hypothesis.
例如 我的假說就是 在你強姦了你女兒之後
For instance, my hypothesis here is that after you raped your daughter,
你強迫她接受電擊休克治療 確保她保持緘默
You submitted her to electroshock treatment to make sure she stayed quiet.
這太無禮了
This is outrageous.
而後 出於內疚 你給她買玩具 更具體地說 你給她買某系列的娃娃
And then,out of guilt, you bought her toys, more specifically, you bought her a line of dolls.
因為 連環猥褻犯都會這麼做的 他們給予禮物
Because that's what serial molesters do. They give gifts.
於是 你和你的其他病患們 也延續了這個模式
So you continued the pattern with your other patients,
而一旦她們不再受你的"照顧" 你就把她們的玩具添到你的收藏
And once they left your care, you added their toys to your collection.
很遺憾 你沒法證實你的故事 博士
I'm sorry,you can't back up your story, doctor.
這就是為什麼我熱愛我的工作 醫生
This is why I love my job,doctor.
因為我的實驗室 就是審你的法庭
Because my lab, it's a jury of your peers.
我的實驗將會是Jenny Larson Abigail Moore還有Linda Krauss
My tests will be jenny larson, abigail moore, and linda krauss.
地檢會讓她們出庭作供 而我會親自把這些娃娃拿上庭
The d.a.will put them on the stand, and I'm  going to personally bring these dolls in,
我們倒要看看 她們作何反應
And we're going to watch how they react.
或著 你可以告訴我們你女兒在哪 那我們可以告訴地檢 你配合調查
Or you could tell us where your daughter is and we'll tell the d.a.you cooperated.
但一旦我們走出這扇門  這交易可以就作廢了
But once we walk out this door, that deal comes off the table.
亞當斯街2529號
2529 adams street.
你會告訴他們的 對吧? 我有配合
You'll tell them,right? That I cooperated.
想知道我是怎麼看穿你的嗎?
You want to know how I figured you out?
那些玩具 你很小心收藏它們 這些你卻當寶貝珍藏
Those toys. You take care of them. These ones you treasured.
但你知道吧? 那些系列並不完整
But you know what? The collection's not complete.
它們在哪?
Where are they?
她要回來了
She's coming back.
我必須得把它再接回去
I have to put it back in.
- 不求你了 請別 - 抱歉
- No,please. Please,don't. - I'm sorry.
別離開我
Don't leave me.
讓我們走
Let us go.
- 我不能 - Samantha?
- I can't. - Samantha?
你好 我叫Spencer 我是FBI的
Uh,my name's spencer. I'm with the fbi.
我知道你父親對你做了什麼
I know what your father did to you,
而且 我希望你能明白 他以後 永遠 再也不能再傷害你了
and I want you to know that he can never, ever hurt you again.
他從來沒碰過我  他是個好父親 他愛我
He never touched me. He's a good father. He loves me.
我知道 他很可能強迫你說這些話
I know that he probably forced you to say those things,
並且如果你說錯 他會懲罰你 把你送到有閃電的房間?
And he punished you if you got it wrong, sent you to the room with the lightning.
是啊
Yeah.
你父親在傷害你之後 給你的那些娃娃 它們會怎樣?
The dolls that your father gave you after he hurt you, what would happen to them?
他把它們跟其它玩具一起 放在他的辦公室
He kept them in his office with the other toys.
他讓你在那婺禰早怐惕a?
That's where he let you play with them?
但當我搬出來的時候  我得帶上我的朋友們
But when I moved out, I had to take my friends with me.
我不能丟下它們
I couldn't leave them behind.
當然 所以你去接它們
Of course. And so you went you get them.
你找...找到了什麼?
What--what did you find?
是啊 他把它們給了另一個女孩 對吧?
Yeah. He gave them to another girl, didn't he?
你想要回它們嗎?
Do you want them back?
他說我不能  他說 送走它們是有好處的
He said I couldn't. He said they were gone for good.
他說謊了 他說謊很長時間了
He lied. He's been lying to you for a long time.
你想見它們嗎?
Do you want to see them?
- 我可以嗎? - 可以 可以 你想跟它們玩嗎?
- Can i? - Yeah. Yeah,do you want to play with them?
安全 我們這婸搨n醫護支援
Clear. We need medical here.
等下 等一下 嘿Samantha? 聽著
Hold on. Hold on one second. Hey,samantha? Listen.
你要跟這個叔叔走 但你的朋友們 也可以跟你一起去好嗎?
You need to go with these men, but your friends can go with you,ok?
他們不會...不會把它們帶走嗎?
They won't take-- they won't take them away?
我保證 沒人會再把它們帶走的
I promise no one will ever take them away again.
幹得好 Reid探員
Well done,agent reid.
謝了
Thanks.
12步之內 將死
Checkmate in 12.
- 不可能 - 我下給你看
- No way. - Let me show you.
艾薩克·阿西莫夫曾寫道: (美國當代科幻小說家)
Isaac asimov wrote,
"人生不像下棋  將死之後 遊戲還會繼續"
"in life,unlike chess, the game continues after checkmate."
犯罪心理 第五季 第12集 怪誕山谷
== 結束 ==
Criminal Minds Season05 Episode12 The Uncanny Valley